YANAN WU

+1 (607) 372-0368 | yxw190021@utdallas.edu

gisynw.com | linkedin.com/in/giswu | github.com/gisynw | ywu120766.medium.com/

SUMMARY

PhD Student in the Geospatial Information Sciences Department at the University of Texas at Dallas. 2 years of teaching experience as an instructor, guiding students to achieve success in learning geographic information science (GIS) and statistics. Excellent written and verbal communication skills evident by extensive conferences and awards. Proven problem-solving, relationship-building, and negotiation through academic and research experience as a Teaching Assistant and a Research Assistant.

EDUCATION

Doctor of Philosophy in Geospatial Information Sciences

May 2024

The University of Texas at Dallas

Master of Science in Geography

May 2019

Binghamton University

Bachelor of Science in Resource Environment and Urban-Rural Planning Management

May 2016

Xi'an University of Science and Technology, China

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Modeling of emergency incidents with GPS trajectory data using machine learning

July 2022 – Present

- · Led the development, training, and testing of machine learning algorithms to predict emergency dispatch
- Established interactive web maps to efficiently display GPS trajectories using ArcGIS for JavaScript and Python
- Delivered 20+ presentations, received 10 travel awards and scholarships, and gained 7 awards in talk competitions

An Integrated Connected Vehicle and Computing Platform for Public Safety Applications

July 2019 - July 2020

- Leveraged Fourier Transformation, A-Priori Algorithm to analyze traffic accidents in Dallas
- Provided quarterly reports to supervisor, published papers and conference proceedings
- Initiated <u>Medium</u> blog posts on machine learning, Web-GIS development, and data processing using R, promoting writing skills and engaging in the online community
- Created and maintained repositories to store, track, and share codes on GitHub

Instructor/Lecturer - Principles of Geospatial Information Sciences

May 2022- May 2023

- Gave lectures and guided students to learn in GIS through class discussions in a traditional or online classroom
- Contributed to the course material on principles of mapping, charting, and data visualization in ArcGIS Pro.
- Facilitated the development of proficiency in the use of Esri products, enhancing students' geospatial data analysis skills.
- Received excellent feedback from students and peer reviews, available on my personal website.

Instructor/Lecturer - Methods of Quantitative Analysis in the Social and Policy Science

May 2021 – May 2022

• Instructed and facilitated discussions with 50 students on fundamental statistical concepts and methods, including statistics, probabilities, sampling, hypothesis tests, and regression.

Integration of Earth Observation and in Situ Data for Analyzing Lake Level Changes

May 2017 - May 2019

• Analyzed and interpreted global remote sensing images and GRACE data using ArcGIS Pro

PUBLICATIONS

Wu, Y., Yang, Y., & Yuan, M. (2023). Location analytics of routine occurrences (LARO) to identify locations with regularly occurring events with a case study on traffic accidents. *Information* (Under review)

Wu, Y., Yang, Y., & Yuan, M. (2023). Understanding the role of geographical environments in emergency dispatches with GPS trajectories. *Abstracts of the ICA*, 6, 276.

Wu, Y., & Yuan, M. (2021). Where and why there: location analytics of routine occurrences (LARO) with a case study on traffic accidents. *Abstracts of the ICA*, 3, 318.

CONFERENCE PROCEEDINGS

Wu, Y., Yang, Y., Yuan, M. Analyze emergency-vehicle dispatches in Dallas, Texas, USA, In AutoCarto 2022 Proceedings.

Yang, Y., Wu, Y., Yuan, M. Quantifying the impacts of social infrastructure on human networks, In AutoCarto 2022 Proceedings.

AWARDS

2023	Second Place in	Graduate Paper	Competition	, SWAAG conference
------	-----------------	-----------------------	-------------	--------------------

- 2023 International Cartographic Association Scholarship
- 2023 Travel award from USNC for ICA with NSF funding to attend the ICC2023
- 2023 Betty & Gifford Johnson Travel Award, UTD
- 2022 Graduate student participants of the Grad WINGS Workshop, UCGIS
- 2022 International Cartographic Association Scholarship
- 2022 Second Place, Student Lightning Talk Award, UCGIS Symposium
- 2022 Third Place in GIS Day 2022 Awarded by Geospatial Information Sciences Program, UTD
- **2022** Travel award from UCGIS to attend the UCGIS Symposium
- 2022 The University of Texas at Dallas 2022 Three Minute Thesis (3MT) Competition, Finalist
- 2022 Honorable mentions, GI Science & Systems Student Honors Paper Competition session, AAG
- 2021 International Cartographic Association Scholarship
- 2021 Travel award from USNC for ICA with NSF funding to attend the ICC2021
- 2021 Pioneers Student Research Fund, Geospatial Information Sciences Program, UTD
- 2021 PhD Research Small Grants Awarded by the Office of Graduate Education, UTD
- 2021 First Place in GIS Day 2021 Awarded by Geospatial Information Sciences Program, UTD
- 2019 First Place in GIS Day 2019 Awarded by Geospatial Information Sciences Program, UTD
- 2019 Pioneers Student Research Fund, Geospatial Information Sciences Program, UTD
- 2019 First Place in GIS Day 2019 Awarded by the Geography Department at Binghamton University
- 2015 Outstanding Prize in GeoDesign at Esri GIS Software Development Contest

PRESENTATIONS

- 2023 Identify geographical environments influencing emergency response performance. SWAAG,
- 2023 Modeling of emergency incident with GPS trajectory data using random forest algorithm. ICC, August
- 2023 Assessing the role of geographical context in modeling the likelihood of emergency response. AAG, April
- 2022 Driving pattern analysis for emergency vehicle (EV). AutoCarto, November
- 2022 Understanding emergency vehicle movement from GPS trajectory data. GIS Day in UTD, November
- 2022 Understanding 911 Response Time from GPS trajectory data. UTD Research Day, October
- 2022 Driving pattern analysis for emergency vehicle (EV) using multi-source data. UCGIS, Syracuse, NY, June
- 2022 Why is there a delay in a 911 vehicle arriving? The Three Minute Thesis (3MT) Competition, UTD, April
- 2022 Location analytics of routine occurrences (LARO) to identify locations with regularly occurring events. CO, April
- 2022 Location Analytics of Routine Occurrences (LARO) with a case study on traffic accidents. AAG, New York, February
- 2021 location analytics of routine occurrences (LARO) with a case study on traffic accidents. ICC, Italy, December
- 2021 Emergency vehicle data map-matching utilizing the Dijkstra's Algorithm. GIS Day in UTD, November
- 2021 Spatial-temporal analysis of traffic accidents for increasing sustainable transportation. The Center for Spatial Studies at UCSB
- 2021 The Three Minute Thesis (3MT) Competition. The University of Texas at Dallas, April
- 2020 Research Showcase Poster Competition, EPPS. The University of Texas at Dallas, October
- 2019 Visualizing (Wild) Fires in Sentinel-2 imagery using custom script in EO Browser. GIS Day in UTD, November
- 2019 Developing an hourly risk model for street networks in Dallas. SWAAG, Fort Worth, Texas. October
- 2019 Integration of Earth observations and in situ data for analyzing lake level changes. GIS Day at Binghamton University, March
- 2019 Integration of Earth observations and in situ data for analyzing lake level changes. AAG, Washington D.C. April

ACADEMIC SERVICE

- 2022 Student judge for Faculty Three Minutes Thesis (3MT) Competition in UTD
- 2022 USGIF Student Assistant Program at the 2022 GEOINT Symposium

PROFESSIONAL MEMBERSHIPS

American Association of Geographers

Cartography and Geographic Information Society